Guide to the Arthur Bliss Lane Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Letters to Arthur Bliss Lane and to Cornelia Baldwin Lane, 1907-1957; Series I; 274 feet 55 Boxes
  - 1950 January 13-1950 May 8 (Box 39, Folder 688-702)
  - 1950 May 9-1950 August 2 (Box 40, Folder 703-716)
  - 1950 August 3-1950 August [no day] (Box 41, Folder 717-724)
  - 1950 September 1-1950 September 30 (Box 41, Folder 725-730)
  - 1950 October 1-1951 January 31 (Box 42, Folder 731-746)
  - 1951 February-1951 May 10 (Box 43, Folder 747-757)
  - 1951 May 16-1951 June 15 (Box 43, Folder 758-762)
  - 1951 June 16-1951 October 10 (Box 44, Folder 763-778)
  - 1951 October 11-1951 [no month] (Box 45, Folder 779-791)
  - 1952 January 1-1952 January 16 (Box 45, Folder 791a-793)
  - 1952 January 17-1952 April 9 (Box 46, Folder 794-808a)
  - 1952 April 10-1952 July 8 (Box 47, Folder 809-823)
  - 1952 July 9-1952 October 15 (Box 48, Folder 824-840)
  - 1952 October 16-1952 November [no day] (Box 49, Folder 841-851)
  - 1952 December 1-1952 December [no day] (Box 49, Folder 852-856)
  - 1953 January 1-1953 January 26 (Box 49, Folder 857-858)
  - 1953 January 27-1953 August 11 (Box 50, Folder 859-877)
  - 1953 August 12-1954 September 20 (Box 51, Folder 878-898)
  - 1954 September 21-1955 May 5 (Box 52, Folder 899-917)
  - 1955 May 6-1955 [no month] (Box 53, Folder 918-932)
  - 1956 January 1-1956 March 18 (Box 53, Folder 933-938)
  - 1956 March 19-1956 July 31 (Box 54, Folder 939-949)
  - 1956 August 1-12 (Box 54, Folder 950)
  - Letters and telegrams to Mrs Cornelia Baldwin Lane concerning the passing away of Arthur Bliss Lane
    - 1956 August 13-1956 August 17 (Box 54, Folder 951-960)
    - 1956 August 18-1956 August 31 (Box 55, Folder 961-966)
    - 1956 August [no day] (1) (Box 55, Folder 967)
    - 1956 August [no day] (2) (Box 55, Folder 968)
    - 1956 August [no day] (3) (Box 55, Folder 969)
    - 1956 September 1-1957 May (Box 55, Folder 970-974)
  - Miscellaneous cards and notes, Undated (Box 55, Folder 974)
- Letters from Arthur Bliss Lane, 1904-1956; Series II; 170" 32 Boxes
  Series II contains letters sent by Arthur Bliss Lane. They are arranged in chronological order, with undated material at the end of the series.
  The last two folders contain correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. James Warren Lane and Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Bliss Lane.
  - 1904-1917 May (Box 56, Folder 975-977b)
  - 1917 July-1917 September (Box 56, Folder 977c-977d)
  - 1918 (Box 56, Folder system_indicator_fc57809a3c985c5376dcc8786225a46f)
  - 1919 (Box 56a, Folder 978-984)
  - 1922-1928 August 10 (Box 56a, Folder 985-994)
  - 1928 August 11-1930 July 17 (Box 57, Folder 995-1017)
  - 1930 July 18-1931 March 31 (Box 58, Folder 1018-1038)
  - 1931 April 1-1933 February 28 (Box 59, Folder 1039-1059)
  - 1933 March 1-1934 April (Box 60, Folder 1060-1084)
  - 1934 May 1-1935 July 31 (Box 61, Folder 1084a-1102)
  - 1935 August 1-1936 April (Box 62, Folder 1103-1121)
  - 1936 May-1936 Dec, undated (Box 63, Folder 1122-1136)
  - 1937 January-February 10 (Box 63, Folder 1137-1138)
  - 1937 February 11-1937 August 31 (Box 64, Folder 1139-1157)
  - 1937 September 1-1939 October (Box 65, Folder 1158-1177)
  - 1939 November-1942 March 22 (Box 66, Folder 1178-1197)
  - 1942 March 23-1943 July (Box 67, Folder 1198-1216)
  - 1943 August-1944 December (Box 68, Folder 1217-1234)
  - 1945 January 1-1946 March (Box 69, Folder 1235-1251)
  - 1946 April-1947 April 10 (Box 70, Folder 1252-1265)
  - 1947 April 11-1947 September 10 (Box 71, Folder 1266-1283)
  - 1947 September 11-1948 March 15 (Box 72, Folder 1284-1300)
  - 1948 March 16-1948 August 23 (Box 73, Folder 1301-1318)
  - 1948 August 24-1949 February 9 (Box 74, Folder 1319-1949)
  - 1949 February 10-1949 July 17 (Box 75, Folder 1337-1355)
  - 1949 July 18-1949 November 15 (Box 76, Folder 1356-1372)
  - 1949 November 16-1950 May 15 (Box 77, Folder 1373-1389)
  - 1950 May 16-1950 August 19 (Box 78, Folder 1390-1406)
  - 1950 August 20-1951 April 3 (Box 79, Folder 1407-1423)
  - 1951 April 4-1951 July (Box 80, Folder 1424-1441)
  - 1951 August 1-1951 December 31 (Box 81, Folder 1442-1458)
  - 1952 January 1-1952 March 31 (Box 82, Folder 1459-1472)
  - 1952 April 1-1952 August 31 (Box 83, Folder 1473-1488)
  - 1952 September 1-1953 January 31 (Box 84, Folder 1489-1504)
  - 1953 February 1-1953 November (Box 85, Folder 1505-1524)
  - 1953 December-1955 March 14 (Box 86, Folder 1525-1543)
  - 1955 March 15-1956 February 29 (Box 87, Folder 1544-1562)
  - 1956 March 1-1956 October (Box 88, Folder 1563-1572)
  - Undated (Box 88, Folder 1573)
    General
    During and post-career.
  - Letters to and from James Warren Lane, 1917 (Box 88, Folder 1573a)
  - Letters to Mrs. James Warren Lane and George Bliss Lane from Cornelia Baldwin, 1917-1918 (Box 88, Folder 1573b)
- Documentary Materials, 1919, 1943-1946; Series III; 12" 3 Boxes
  Documentary Materials contains documents, reports, typescripts, articles, newspaper clippings, minutes and printed materials. This series is arranged by type within each type. The material is then in chronological order.
  Topics include the Versaille Treaty, the Congressional investigation of the Katyn Forest Massacre, the Kohlberg Matter, the Retired Diplomatic and Consular Officer's Meetings and the Yalta Conference.
  - Versailles Peace Conference -- Treaty of Peace and Protocol, 1919 (Box 89, Folder 1574)
  - Yalta Conference --- Documents and Ancillary Materials, 1944-1945 (Box 89, Folder 1575)
  - American Committee for the Investigation of the Katyn Massacre
    - By-laws, Certificate of Incorporation, Report, 1949-1950 (Box 90, Folder 1576)
    - Press Releases, 1949 (Box 90, Folder 1576)
  - American Committee for the Investigation of the Katyn Massacre
    - Accountant's Report, Undated (Box 90, Folder 1577)
    - Financial Records, 1950-1952 (Box 90, Folder 1577)
  - Katyn Massacre Investigation
    - Governmental Statements, Press Releases, Reports, 1945-1952 (Box 90, Folder 1578)
    - Congressional Hearings, 1952 Mar, Jun, November (Box 90, Folder 1579)
    - Congressional Record excerpts, 1949-1952 (Box 90, Folder 1580)
    - Magazine articles, newspaper clippings, 1949-1952 (Box 90, Folder 1580)
  - Katyn Massacre
    - The Katyn Wood Murder, a typescript by Joseph Mackiewicz, 222 pages, Undated (Box 91, Folder 1581)
    - The Mass Murder of Polish of Prisoners of War in Katyn, 31 pages, 1946 November (Box 91, Folder 1582)
    - The Mysteries of the Van Vliet Report, Julius Epstein, 15 pages, 1951 (Box 91, Folder 1583)
  - Polish Association of Former Soviet Political Prisoners
    - Articles, press releases, 1943 (Box 91, Folder 1584)
  - Fliers' Memorial, 1950 (Box 91, Folder 1585)
  - Kohlberg Matter -- Hearings, articles, letters, press releases, 1948-1950 (Box 91, Folder 1586)
  - Kidnapping of the Russian Seamen -- Congressional report, magazine article, 1956 (Box 91, Folder 1587)
  - Diplomatic and Consular Officers, Retired
    - By-laws and proposed amendments, 1950-1955 (Box 91, Folder 1588)
    - Minutes of Executive Committee meetings, 1955-1956 (Box 91, Folder 1589)
    - Annual Members Meeting, 1955-1956 (Box 91, Folder 1590)
    - Financial Statements, 1954-1955 (Box 91, Folder 1591)
    - Dacor House, 1954-1955 (Box 91, Folder 1592)
  - Miscellaneous Reports, 1955, undated (Box 91, Folder 1593)
  - National Committee for Free Europe -- Declaration of policy, memorandum on organization and operations, stand on Polish disunity, printed materials, 1949 June-September (Box 91, Folder 1594)
- Personal Materials, 1916-1952 1954, 1956; Series IV; 1 linear foot (3 boxes, 1oversize folio)
  Personal Materials contains presidential diplomas, a marriage certificate, personal memorabilia, appointment books, obituaries, testimonials and letters recommending Arthur Bliss Lane to Secretary of State, Robert S. Lansing.
  - Presidential diploma testifying to the appointment of Arthur Bliss Lane as U.S. Envoy to Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania, 1936 (Box 92, Folder 1595)
  - Presidential diploma testifying to the appointment of Arthur Bliss Lane as U.S. Envoy to Yugoslavia, 1937 (Box 92, Folder 1596)
  - Presidential diploma testifying to the appointment of Arthur Bliss Lane as U.S. Envoy to Costa Rica, 1941 (Box 92, Folder 1597)
  - Certificate of Marriage, 1918 (Box 93, Folder 1598)
  - Volume of Personal Memorablia, 1916-1918 (Box 93, Folder 1599)
  - Guest Book, 1918-1944 (Box 94, Folder 1600)
  - Pocket Appointment Books, 1939-1952, 1954 (Box 94, Folder 1601)
  - Large Appointment Books, 1946, 1947 (Box 95, Folder 1602)
  - Large Appointment Book, 1951 (Box 95, Folder 1603)
  - Investment Book, 1927-1933 (Box 95, Folder 1604)
  - Investment Books, 1940-1948, 1950-1952 (Box 95, Folder 1605)
  - Dinner Cards and Wine List, 1931-1937 (Box 95, Folder 1606)
  - Obituaries and Eulogy, 1956 (Box 95, Folder 1607)
  - Testimonial of Commendation from the Polish-American Congress, 1947 (Box 95, Folder 1607a)
  - Letters to Secretary of State Robert S. Lansing recommending Arthur Bliss Lane, 1917 (Box 95, Folder 1607b)
- Writings, 1941, 1947-1956; Series V; 15" 3 Boxes
  Writings contains the typescript of I Saw Poland Betrayed, published and unpublished articles, book reviews for The Journal of Central European Affairs, speeches and lectures, broadcasts, research material on Yugoslavia, and other people's writings.
  The series is arranged by type of material. Within each type, the material is arranged alphabetically by title for books, articles and reviews, and is arranged chronologically for speeches, lectures and broadcasts.
  - Books: I Saw Poland Betrayed Typescript, 1948 (Box 96, Folder 1608)
  - Books: I Saw Poland Betrayed Carbon copy, photos and captions, mailing list for comp. copies (Box 96, Folder 1609)
  - Books: I Saw Poland Betrayed Published copy, 1948 (Box 96, Folder 1609a)
  - Books: Autobiography (unpublished), Undated (Box 97, Folder 1610)
  - Articles: "Conquest in Yugoslavia," Life, 1941 September (Box 97, Folder 1611)
  - Articles: "How Russia Rules Poland," Life, 1947 July 14 (Box 97, Folder 1612)
  - Articles: "Poland," Encyclopedia Americana, 1948 November 11 (Box 97, Folder 1613)
  - Articles: "Trip to Europe" (unpublished), 1951 (Box 97, Folder 1614)
  - Articles: "The Truth About the Katyn Forest Massacre," American Legion Magazine, 1952 February (Box 97, Folder 1615)
  - Articles: "Brilliant Chapter," National Review, 1956 January 4 (Box 97, Folder 1616)
  - Book Reviews for Journal of Central European Affairs, Undated (Box 97, Folder 1617)
  - Speeches and Lectures, 1947-1949 Nov, 1950-1956 (Box 97, Folder 1618-1624)
  - Broadcasts:
    - WCBS, 1947 April 5 (Box 98, Folder 1625)
    - New Orleans, 1948 February (Box 98, Folder 1625)
    - WJZ, 1948 April 7 (Box 98, Folder 1625)
  - Broadcasts:
    - Shortwave broadcast to Italy, WRUL, 1948 April 8 (Box 98, Folder 1626)
    - ABC "Town Meeting of the Air", 1948 October 5 (Box 98, Folder 1626)
  - Research Material on Yugoslavia -- Newspaper clippings, 1941 (Box 98, Folder 1627)
  - Research Material on Yugoslavia, 1949, 1951 (Box 98, Folder 1628-1629)
  - Other People's Writings
    - Clair Booth Luce, 1947 May 28 (Box 98, Folder 1630)
    - Broadcast mentioning Arthur Bliss Lane, 1948 (Box 98, Folder 1631)
- Printed Matter, 1929-1956; Series VI; 8" 2 Boxes
  Printed Matter contains government reports, reprints, news-letters, bulletins and informational materials. The series is arranged chronologically with undated material at the end.
  - Printed Matter
    - 1929-1952 (Box 99, Folder 1632-1636)
    - 1952-1956, undated (Box 100, Folder 1637-1639)
- Press Releases, 1947, 1949-1953; Series VII; 3" 1 Box
  Press Releases are arranged chronologically. They include statements by Arthur Bliss Lane, John Foster Dulles, Robert Taft and others. Topics include Dean Acheson's appointment as Secretary of State, and Alger Hiss.
  - Press Releases, 1947, 1949-1953 (Box 101, Folder 1640-1642)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1920-1925, 1936-1956; Series VIII; .75 linear feet (3 boxes, one oversize folio)
  Newspaper clippings are arranged chronologically. They concern Arthur Bliss Lane's public statements and actions.
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1920-1925, 1936-1947, 1948 February to Dec, 1949-1951 (Box 102, Folder 1643-1651)
    - 1952-1956 (Box 103, Folder 1652-1655)
    - Oversize, 1956 August (Box 103a, Folder 1655a)
- Photographs, 1894, 1917-1922, 1925-1930, 1933-1934; Series IX; 5.5 linear feet (7 boxes, two oversize folios)
  Photographs contains personal and official photos. They are arranged by the nation in which they were photographed. Within each country, they are arranged chronologically.
  Topics include family activities in Rome and Poland, Henry Wallace's visit to Colombia (1943) and the Moscow Conference (1943).
  - Childhood, 1894 (Box 104, Folder 1656)
  - Wedding, 1918 (Box 104, Folder 1657)
  - Family Pictures, Undated (Box 104, Folder 1658)
  - Rome, 1917-1918 (Box 104, Folder 1658)
  - Family Pictures, 1918-1922 (Box 104, Folder 1659)
  - Poland, 1919, 1925 (Box 104, Folder 1659)
  - Family Pictures, 1920's, early (Box 105, Folder 1660)
  - Mexico, 1925-1929 (Box 105, Folder 1661)
  - Mexico, 1925-1930 (Box 106, Folder 1662-1663)
  - Central America, 1933, 1936 (Box 107, Folder 1664)
  - Italy, 1934 (Box 107, Folder 1664)
  - France, 1934 (Box 107, Folder 1664)
  - Mexico, 1933 (Box 107, Folder 1665)
  - Nicaragua, 1933-1934 (Box 107, Folder 1665)
  - Latvia, 1936-1937 (Box 108, Folder 1666)
  - Russia, 1936 (Box 108, Folder 1666)
  - Germany, 1937 (Box 108, Folder 1666)
  - Yugoslavia, 1937-1940 (Box 108, Folder 1667)
  - Yugoslavia, 1942 (Box 108A)
    Oversize color photograph of Peter II, king of Yugoslavia, signed July 25, 1942.
  - France, 1937 (Box 108, Folder 1667)
  - Austria, Germany, Poland, 1937 (Box 109, Folder 1668)
  - Colombia, South America, 1941-1943 (Box 110, Folder 1669)
  - Colombia, Henry Wallace's visit to, 1943 (Box 110, Folder 1670)
  - Colombia, 1943 (Box 110, Folder 1671)
  - Moscow Conference, 1943 (Box 111, Folder 1672)
  - Germany, 1945 (Box 111, Folder 1672)
  - Poland, 1945 (Box 111, Folder 1672)
  - Poland, 1945, circa 1945-1947 (Box 111, Folder 1673-1674)
- Phonograph Records, 1950, 1952; Series X
  Phonograph Records contains two recordings of addresses and a radio interview on the Longinie Chronoscope.
  Topics concern the Katyn Forest Massacre and Korea.
  * Transferred to Historical Sound Recordings 9 Jul 1979.
  - Address on the Katyn Forest Massacre (*), 1950
  - Address on Korea, with references to atrocities in general, Poland and the Katyn Forest Massacre (*), 1952
  - Radio interview on the Longinie Chronoscope (4 records, 1 is a duplicate) (*), 1952
- 1970 Additions, 1917, 1953-1956; Series XI
  - Intergovernmental Committee on European Migration
    - Correspondence, 1953 January-1956 May (Box 114, Folder 1-5)
  - Financial records and correspondence, 1953 November-1954 October (Box 114, Folder 6)
  - Foreign Service League of the United States (Constitution, bylaws, etc.), 1955-1956, undated (Box 114, Folder 7)
  - Notes written on trans-Atlantic journey, [1917 Jul?] (Box 114, Folder 8)